hello everyone my name is greg and i def
staff welcome everyone to episode 3 of
the tactics gaming unity in this episode
we will make some small optimization and
elevation
so in the last episode i promised i will
explain some some of the problems with
the system and in what cases you want to
keep it as is and when you want to
change it
look at this grid right now this grid
can exist anywhere i can move it like
this but the problem is if you look into
the calculation of the selected node
it has those additional steps to take
into account the position
which is not a lot but will impact the
performance unnecessary
so what we want to do is to assume that
our point of origin will always be in 00
position
but in what cases you don't want to do
it you may ask
in cases where you want to keep an
ability to move your grid around and
place it in any spot on the scene here
is hypothetical example an fps game
where you find a chess puzzle in the
level and this chess puzzle is separate
grid object placed somewhere in the
level and because we don't fix our
position of origin to 000 position
game designer will be able to move this
grid anymore on the scene
bar the ability to rotate it around but
it can be actually implemented if you
want
in our case because we are making
tactics rpg we will benefit from doing
those optimization steps
while small it will adds up so let's do
them
move the map into 0 position
make sure you are moving the grid object
and not the terrain object
reduce the calculation of position with
the assumption that we will be placing
our grid in 00 position
in get grid position we just need to
remove the offset applied to the past
world position
and in get world position remove the
transform position which applies offset
to the world position based on the
position of the grid in the world
now everything should work exactly as it
used to work
this episode is brought to you by
generous support of people on patreon
and members on youtube if you want to
join them link to my patreon in the
description and join button available
right now on youtube
good now let's introduce an elevation of
the node
into the game so right now each node has
same elevation as any other node what we
want to do is to determine the elevation
of each node when this node is created
so let's create an area to play around
create an empty object called terrain
move it to 000 position
when we are creating the area let's hide
the characters and grid with obstacles
by pressing this log button
this way we can concentrate on making
terrain
so let's create two planes
actually we need to see the grid to know
to what scale are we building our map
so let's change grid gizmos
here instead of exiting out of the draw
gizmo if the array of node is no we will
only draw the node just for visual
reference
good
now even in the non-play mode we can see
nodes
actually you know let's use unity
terrain feature i think this will be a
better approach
create a terrain object now let's start
shaping our playing field
make the terrain smaller and let's make
the terrain green
this is not how you use terrain this is
just for demonstration purposes we will
be making our scene looks better later
on in this tutorial
and yes the material setup is incorrect
again this is just for the demonstration
purposes
so let's rise the terrain and let's draw
one place for the river to pass through
make the plane object to draw the water
level for the river
and add the box to represent the bridge
parent all of this to the grid
now we will determine the elevation of
each node
so open the grid script
in the generate grid create and call a
new method called calculate elevation
inside this method we want to simply
shoot array from
above until we hit the terrain from each
possible position of the node
and read the position of the collision
to determine the elevation of the point
create a ray in the world position
and pointing down
shoot the ray using raycast
we need to create a new serialized
variable for train layer
and after that read hit point to get the
y position which will represent the
elevation of the node store the
elevation into the node by creating a
new variable for it
take into the account the elevation in
get world position
to avoid potentially getting errors in
the editor because you trying to access
grid without initiating it yet let's add
parameters called elevation into the get
world position and in case it is true
return elevation otherwise returns zero
set the terrain layer field and launch
the game
we have forgotten to offset the ray
above the ground
so add the
vector up multiplied by 100 so you will
offset the origin point of your ray
hundred points above which
generally translates into hundred meters
this is weird
for some reason there is
nothing in the elevation
let's debug together
what we need to do is to read the code
line by line from where we begin
logically of course we don't need to
look into everything
and
look what our code is doing to try to
find where the error is
so
look into the generated grid okay we
initialize the grid array good then we
cycle through the grid and create nodes
that is good
then we calculate the elevations
good
and then we determine the possible
terrain where we can pass or not
and here you can see that we are
rewriting the state of the node by
creating it again
and this is all culprit
let's test this
good now you can see that at run time
game will determine the elevation
so now let's talk a little about the
obstacles you see obstacles objects
allow us to block out the possible and
impossible terrain very quickly
just set the shape of the river and this
river is going to be marked as
impossible terrain for us
this
will allow you to easily modify and
change the maps
but remember
right now
the map data is generated at the start
so if you move the obstacle at runtime
it will not change the state of the
nodes at runtime
remember that later on we will be able
to use the exactly same systems for for
example marking the forest
tiles or nodes or marking the difficult
terrain etc etc
so let's create another new script
called delete me which will clear the
obstacles of the scene on the start
and this is our implementation of
elevation
now if i do any modification to terrain
it should recognize the new elevation
or if i create an object and assign him
to the terrain layer it should read and
recognize it as terrain allowing you to
for example make fights on top of
buildings or any other objects
in the next episode we will be dealing
with pathfinding wish me luck
good this is it for this episode if you
have any questions or any ideas about
code please leave your comment below if
you're interested in seeing what will
come out of this please subscribe
if you want to support further you can
find my patreon in the description
special thank you to andrew v long and
this old hash do for their generous
support with best regards see in the
next episode
you